now that we have seen that some
dependencies can become hazards in our
pipeline now we need to see how to
handle these hazards so that we still
get correct execution in our pipeline
because we cannot just allow the
pipeline to produce incorrect results we
need to handle only the situations that
are hazards we don't really care about
dependencies that can never become
hazards in fact what we need to do is
detect hazard situations and then either
flush dependent instructions from the
pipeline stall dependent instructions in
the pipeline so that the read is delayed
and they get the correct value or even
fixed values that were read already by
the dependent instructions so that we
feed them the right value and they
proceed unharmed through the pipeline we
need to use flushes for control
dependencies because the instructions we
have in the pipeline after a control
dependence becomes a hazard are the
wrong instructions so delaying them or
trying to fix the values that they are
reading is not going to work pretty much
we have to delete these instructions
from the pipeline and fetch the correct
ones and then execute them from scratch
so we need to flush the dependent
instructions on a control dependence if
we have a data dependence we can stall
the subtract so that it stays in the
stage where it would read r1 until
finally they are deposits that value in
the register so for hazards caused by
data dependencies we do not have to
flush we can simply stall for some data
dependencies we can even forward the
value of r1 produced by the add to the
subtract in a way that fixes the value
read by the subtract let's consider our
five stage pipeline and just worry about
the stage where we read the registers
and the alias stage in a cycle where the
subtract is reading the registers the
add is in the ALU stage at the end of
this cycle the subtract has read the
wrong register value for r1 because r1
still doesn't have what add will
eventually write to it but the add at
the end of this cycle has the value
adjusted
didn't put it in our one yet what we now
can do is at the beginning of the
following cycle subtract can get the
value that the ad produced and that
value replaces the value that we read
from our one so that subtract computes
with the correct value so pretty much if
the value exists somewhere in the
pipeline at the point before we actually
use the value to compute we can fix what
we have read so that we still compute
with the right value this is called
forwarding and it amounts to pretty much
fixing the values right by dependent
instructions forwarding does not always
work sometimes the value we need will be
produced at a later point in time so at
the time we need it to compute we still
don't even have that value in the
pipeline at that time we need to stall
instead of forwarding so basically for
control hazards we need to flush for
some data hazards we can either store
forward and we prefer forwarding because
it doesn't introduce stalls in the
pipeline and for some data hazards at
least some stalls are necessary